Guide to the Stern Family Papers, 1922-1948, 1971-1996 and undated RL.10986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stern family papers
1922-1948, 1971-1996 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stern family
RL.10986
1.4 Linear Feet
Sidney J. Stern was born in Wilson, NC in 1879 and married Flora Oettinger of Kinston, NC in 1910. The Sterns were active in civic affairs and religious life in Greensboro, where Sidney practiced law until his death in 1947. The materials in this collection primarily document Sidney J. Stern’s efforts to relocate family members and others living in Germany between 1936 and 1948 and to a lesser degree the Stern family’s life and activities in Greensboro, NC. Other materials in the collection include articles, newspaper clippings, and genealogical information on the Oettinger side of the family.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical note
Sidney J. Stern was born in Wilson (Wilson Co.), North Carolina, in 1879 and grew up in Scotland Neck (Halifax Co.), NC, where he eventually became a grocer and member of the city council. In 1908, he left his business to attend law school at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. In 1910, he married Flora Oettinger (1884-1970) of Kinston (Lenoir Co.), NC, and the couple moved to Greensboro (Guilford Co.), NC where Sidney practiced law until his death in 1947.
The Sterns were active in civic affairs and religious life in Greensboro. Sidney served as president of the congregation of Temple Emanuel from [1924?] to 1947. In 1923, the Sterns founded the Homes Building Company, Inc., to construct affordable houses in the Piedmont Heights area of Greensboro.
Collection Overview
The materials in this collection primarily document Sidney J. Stern’s efforts to relocate family members and others living in Germany between 1936 and 1941 and, to a lesser degree, the Stern family’s life and activities in Greensboro (Guilford Co.), North Carolina. The approximately 245 letters related to the relocation of family members include requests for biographical information for visa applications and copies of affidavits of support sworn by Stern and other residents of Greensboro and North Carolina. Other materials in the collection include articles, newspaper clippings, and genealogical information on the Oettinger family of Kinston (Lenoir Co.), N.C.
Related Materials
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina records, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Stern family papers are a gift of Katherine Stern Weaver. They were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University, as part of the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection in June 2014.
Germany -- Emigration and immigration -- History -- 1933-1945; Jews -- North Carolina; United States -- Emigration and immigration -- History -- 20th century; Lawyers -- North Carolina -- Greensboro; Greensboro (N.C.) -- Religious life and customs; Jewish refugees -- United States; Stern family
- Stern Family papers, 1922-1948, 1971-1996 and undated; 1
  - Correspondence, 1936; 1 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1937; 2 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1938, January-July; 3 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1938, August-October; 4 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1938, November-1939, January; 5 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1939, February-December; 6 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1942; 7 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1948; 8 of 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Sidney Joseph Stern...Corresondence from 1936-1944: his efforts before and during World War II to help Jewish relatives and others out of Germany" (spiral-bound photocopies of correspondence) (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Duplicates of original correspondence also found in the collection
  - Biographical and genealogical information and clippings, 1922-1938, 1989 and undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Reflections of a lawyer in epigrams" by Sidney J. Stern, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stern home-building business: clippings and description, 1923, circa 1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The teacher who never knew a dumb child" (history paper on Ruth Rypins), 1989 December (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Materials on various Jewish residents of Greensboro, NC, 1928-1929, 1971-1996 and undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Scope and Contents note
    Primarily obitiuaries and other newspaper clippings. Includes an account of the life of Julius W. Cone, written by Edward T. Cone (1979)
  - Temple Emanuel (Greensboro, NC) 75th anniversary brochure, clipping, 1982, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)